# 福建·晋江
Jinjiang, Fujian
# 来
Come on
# 跟着我步履蹒跚的脚步
Follow my shambling footsteps
# 我们要去吃 壶仔饭
We are heading to: "huzaifan" ("Pot Meal")
# 走吧
Let's go
# 三步
Three steps
# 走啦
Let's go
# 接着上
Keep climbing
# （为什么叫壶仔饭）
因为装饭的罐子
(Why is it called "huzaifan" "pot meal"?)
Because of jars?
# 它这个不是 这个是一个壶
It's not. This is a pot
# 这个是壶嘛
This is a pot, right?
# 这个是
This is it
# 这个就叫壶仔
This is called "huzai"
# 小壶仔
Small "huzai"
# （用壶仔做出来的饭）
Meals made with "huzai" pots
# 明白了
Got it
# 那边还是炒熟的糯米是吧 （糯米啊）
- Over there, is it fried sticky rice?
- Yeah, sitcky rice
# 需要先炒一炒
Gotta stir fry it first?
# 对呀
Yeah
# 泡一下
And soak it
# 再放油
And then add in oil
# 炒 搅拌 搅拌 要搅很久的
Stir fry, and stir, and stir. It takes a long time
# 里面再放那个骨头汤
And also add the bone broth
# 还得放骨头汤
Also add bone broth?
# 当然了 这个挺鲜的骨头汤
Of course. The bone broth is very good
# 哦 明白了
Oh, I see
# 得蒸多久
How long is the steaming time?
# 啊？
Pardon?
# 得蒸多久
How long is the steaming time?
# 10几分钟
10 minutes or so
# 用高压锅 ？（对呀）
- With a pressure cooker?
- Yeah
# 就像家里的粽子那样
Like zongzi we eat at home
# 它蒸的就是很烂
It's steamed to really soft
# 看到她们把壶仔饭从小陶器当中
It's very interesting to see how they
# （用筷子）转出来 还是很有意思的
take the rice out from the clay jar with a chopstick
# （旁边的阿姨）这里面有什么
What are the ingredients, auntie?
# 有莲子 有肉
Lotus seeds, and meat
# 有莲子有肉
Lotus seeds and meat
# 有香菇
And shiitake mushrooms
# 香菇
Shiitake mushrooms
# 饭多少钱
How much is the rice?
# 3块
3 yuan
# （拿一碗饭吧）
(Let's take a bowl of rice)
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 这个壶仔饭就是
This huzaifan
# 颜色比较淡一些
has a relatively light color
# 它是糯米做的
It's made with sticky rice
# 吃起来有点黏牙
so it's a little sticky
# 里面放了一些杂粮
There are some coarse grains in it
# 比如说莲子
For example, lotus seeds
# 所以说 吃起来还有一些的苦味
So, there's also a little bitterness
# 夏天吃挺好的
Pretty good for summers
# 吃起来还有肉的香味
There's also the flavor of meat
# 很多都是年纪比较大的
Many are elderlies here
# 拿着一碗饭 然后
Take a bowl of rice, and
# 配一碗汤来吃
eat with a bowl of soup
# 这家店在这儿是最老的
This is the oldest restaurant around
# 这边比较老的
Oh, an older one here
# 最老的罐子饭
Oldest "guanzifan" ("Can Meal") restaurant
# 哦 它也叫罐子饭
Oh, it's also called "guanzifan"?
# 对 可以叫壶仔饭 也叫罐子饭
Right. Can be "huzaifan", or "guanzifan"
# 两种都一样
Both mean the same thing
# 都可以
Both work
# 只摆了三张桌子的小店
This cozy place with only three tables
# 中午还是很忙碌的
is quite busy at noon
# 关 注
# 雪 鱼 探 店
(Subscribe)